♪The spring breeze blows through the world♪
♪ลมวสันต์พัดผ่านหมู่ชน♪
♪Blowing across the willow bank and the peach blossoms are brilliant♪
♪พัดกิ่งหลิวพลิ้วไหว ดอกท้อช่างดูสดใส♪
♪Who picks up the pen and writes that it's not too late to meet♪
♪ใครกันเล่าเขียนไว้ ไม่นานคงได้พบกัน♪
♪Looking back to see someone smiling happily♪
♪หันกลับไปมอง จึงเห็นรอยยิ้มงดงาม♪
♪Adding a touch of intensity to the depth of love♪
♪ในห้วงลึกของใจ ต่อเติมเส้นสายความรู้สึก♪
♪Being with you in the world of mortals♪
♪ในโลกกว้างใหญ่ มีเจ้าเป็นเพื่อนร่วมทาง♪
♪Whether it is a hustle or plain life♪
♪ไม่ว่าชีวิตจะสงบหรือวุ่นวาย♪
♪There will be no regrets in my life♪
♪ชาตินี้ไม่มีเสียดาย ไม่คิดขัดเคือง♪
♪See you in the next hundred years♪
♪สัญญาจะอยู่ด้วยกันจนวันสุดท้าย ไม่ลืมปัจจุบันที่เรายังเป็นหนุ่มสาว♪
♪I wish to stay and live up to the passing years♪
♪ไม่อยากปล่อยเวลาให้สูญเปล่า♪
♪Every morning and every night we are together♪
♪ทุกค่ำเช้าให้เรามีเรา♪
♪It turned out we've known each other since the beginning♪
♪ที่แท้ความรู้สึกใกล้ชิด เกิดขึ้นเพียงชั่วขณะจิต♪
♪He sent me a thousand words♪
♪เขาส่งจดหมายเนื้อความยาวเหยียด♪
♪She left a story♪
♪นางฝากเรื่องราวจารึกเอาไว้♪
♪The sound of guqin is like water and the shadow of the light is like a dream♪
♪เสียงพิณเสนาะโสต แสงโคมไฟราวอยู่ในฝัน♪
♪Everything is tactful♪
♪โลกใบนี้ช่างแสนงดงาม♪
♪Looking at the scenery and mountains with you♪
♪ได้อยู่ดูโลกกับเจ้า♪
♪The rest of my life will last in perfection♪
♪ใช้ชีวิตที่เหลือเคียงข้างกัน♪
♪Wait until the spring breeze blows♪
♪จนลมวสันต์พัดผ่านมาอีกครั้ง♪
♪That's when I know your deepest love, and I'll miss♪
♪จึงรู้ว่ารักลึกซึ้งสุดหัวใจ♪
=A Female Student Arrives at the Imperial College=
=ศิษย์สาวป่วนสำนัก=
=Episode 20=
=ตอนที่ 20=
Young Master!
คุณชาย
I've brought you the list of appointments you asked for.
รายชื่อแต่งตั้งที่ท่านต้องการมาแล้ว
(Decree)
(หนังสือรายงาน)
Zhuo Wen Yuan, appointed as Vice Minister of the Ministry of Personnel.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน ตำแหน่งซื่อหลางกรมขุนนาง
This guy
เจ้านี่
usually fools around.
ปกติเอาแต่กินเที่ยวดื่มไม่เคยขาด
But to think he would be able
กลับสอบได้ตำแหน่งดีเช่นนี้
to get such good results.
ไม่ธรรมดาจริง ๆ
It appears that Miss Sang...
เหมือนว่าคุณหนูซางจะ...
I expected she wouldn't be appointed.
ข้าเดาได้แต่แรกแล้วว่า นางจะไม่ได้รับตำแหน่งใด
(Imperial College)
(สำนักศึกษา)
Please enjoy yourselves today.
วันนี้ทุกคนก็สนุกกันได้เต็มที่
I have prepared
ข้าเตรียมสุราทำจากผลไม้
fruit wine that has a low alcohol content.
ที่ดื่มแล้วไม่เมาเอาไว้ให้ทุกคน
I've already informed Scholar Feng as well.
และบอกกับอาจารย์เฝิงไว้แล้ว
So he won't
ดังนั้น
suddenly show up
เขาจะไม่โผล่มา
and punish you.
ลงโทษพวกเจ้าแน่
A toast to Deputy Chief.
คารวะซือเย่
- Come. Have a seat. - Have a seat.
- มา มา - นั่ง นั่ง นั่ง
Have a seat.
นั่งสิ
It has been a while.
ไม่เจอกันนานเลย
Indeed.
นั่นสิ
Zhuo.
พี่จั๋ว
You scored the highest results,
ท่านสอบได้ที่หนึ่ง
and you were appointed as the Vice Minister of the Ministry of Personnel.
ซ้ำยังรับตำแหน่งซื่อหลางกรมขุนนาง
Your future will be prosperous indeed.
อนาคตรุ่งเรืองแล้ว
How did that saying go again?
เหมือนที่เขาว่ากันว่า
When you get lucky...
รำมวยแล้ว...
"Don't forget your friends when you get rich".
ร่ำรวยแล้ว อย่าลืมกันต่างหาก
It's no wonder you didn't make the ranks.
มิน่าเจ้าถึงได้สอบไม่ติด
Who cares?
ช่างมันเถอะ
I must get on Zhuo's good side first.
ข้าจะเกาะขาพี่จั๋วไว้แน่น ๆ
Don't forget about your old classmate
ภายหน้าได้ดีแล้ว
in the future.
อย่าลืมสหายเก่าอย่างข้าเล่า
Of course, I wouldn't.
ไม่มีทางหรอก
We are all classmates.
พวกเราต่างเป็นศิษย์ร่วมสำนัก
Please continue to look after me in the future.
วันหน้าข้ายังต้องให้พวกเจ้าสนับสนุน
So humble.
เจ้าถ่อมตัวเกินไปแล้ว
But speaking of which,
จะว่าไป
Deputy Chief Yan's teaching was exceptional
ปีนี้ผลงานการสอนของเยี่ยนซือเย่
this year.
ดีมาก
And I heard he went to Grand Commandant Sang's Residence to ask for his daughter's hand.
ได้ยินว่าไปสู่ขอคนที่จวนซางไท่เว่ยอีก
I suppose he is going to acquire success in both love and career this year.
สมหวังทั้งการงานทั้งความรัก
Didn't that fell through?
ไหนว่าสู่ขอไม่สำเร็จไง
Then...
นั่น...
Since it fell through,
นั่นเมื่อไม่สำเร็จ
it doesn't count.
ก็ยังไม่ได้ผูกดวงเกิด
Even if Grand Commandant Sang agreed, the marriage could be canceled at any time.
ต่อให้สู่ขอสำเร็จ ก็ถอนหมั้นได้
Even if they were married,
ต่อให้แต่งแล้ว
they could still get divorced.
ก็หย่าได้ไม่ใช่หรือ
That is why they say that you sure can be sure about your drinking capacity,
สุรารินเต็มแก้วได้
but don't be so sure about your words.
แต่คำพูดอย่าให้เต็มปากเต็มคำนัก
All right. All right. Zhuo.
ได้ ได้ พี่จั๋ว พี่จั๋ว
Please. Let's enjoy the dishes.
กินข้าว กินข้าว
Yan Yan, have you seen Sang Qi?
เหยียนเหยี่ยน เจ้าพบซางฉีหรือไม่
Drinking your sorrows away?
ใช้สุราย้อมใจเหรอ
But you can't get drunk off of this.
แต่สุรานี่ดื่มยังไงก็ไม่เมา
I'm not.
ไม่ได้ย้อมใจ
I'm trying to summon courage.
ข้ากำลังรวบรวมความกล้า
I took this opportunity
ไม่ง่ายกว่าจะฉวยโอกาส
and got out of the house.
หนีออกมาได้ในงานเลี้ยงรับตำแหน่ง
Deputy Chief,
ซือเย่
why don't you help cover for me while I go to see Lian Pian?
ไม่สู้ท่านช่วยปิดบังพาข้า ไปหาเหลียนเพียนที่จวนไท่เว่ยหน่อย
You promised you would
เจ้าเคยสัญญาว่า
bring Lian Pian happiness, didn't you?
จะทำให้เหลียนเพียนมีความสุขใช่ไหม
Then, you should think things through
เช่นนั้นเจ้าก็ควรคิดทุกอย่าง
carefully.
ให้กระจ่าง
And you must persevere.
แล้วก็ต้องเป็นตัวของตัวเอง
But don't drink.
ดื่มสุราก็ช่างเถอะ
Drinking won't solve your problems.
ดื่มไปแก้ปัญหาไม่ได้
What's going on, Yan Yan?
เหยียนเหยี่ยนเอ๋ย ไหวไม่ไหว
You only drank a few cups of wine, and you're already tipsy?
เพิ่งดื่มไปไม่เท่าไรก็หงอยแบบนี้แล้ว
Song Luo Tian.
ซ่งลั่วเทียน
You're heartless indeed.
เจ้ามันคนไร้หัวจิตหัวใจ
You're acting high and mighty
ปากกล้าไปทั่ว
as if you were the top scholar.
คงว่าตัวเองติดจอหงวนหรือไง
You didn't even make it into the list!
มา มา มา
Just wait and see.
คอยดูเถอะ
You got into that Prefecture Court or something, didn't you?
เจ้าก็แค่สอบติดจวนจิงจ้าวมิใช่เหรอ
Who knows
อนาคต
who will serve the other in the future?
ยังไม่แน่ว่าใครต้องคำนับใครกันแน่
(Imperial College) Young Lady, I'm fine.
(สำนักศึกษา) คุณหนูข้าไม่เป็นไร
Today is the announcement of the results.
วันนี้เป็นวันประกาศผลสอบ เลี้ยงฉลองรับตำแหน่ง
I won't spoil your mood.
ข้าไม่อยากทำให้ท่านเศร้าหมองไปด้วย
I feel happy too.
ข้าก็ดีใจเหมือนกัน
What are you saying?
เจ้าพูดอะไรของเจ้ากัน
It's fine if you're unhappy.
ไม่สบายใจก็ไม่สบายใจสิ
I have ways to cheer you up.
พี่สาวอย่างข้าหา ทางทำให้เจ้าเบิกบานได้เอง
(Imperial College) The Imperial College is holding a banquet today.
วันนี้สำนักศึกษาจัดงานเลี้ยง
After we see the results,
เดี๋ยวดูผลสอบแล้ว
I'll treat you to a feast and a good time, all right?
ข้าจะพาเจ้าไปเลี้ยงมื้อใหญ่ ดีไหม
You're the one who is expecting good results.
ท่านต่างหากมีเรื่องมงคล
Why are we celebrating for me instead?
ทำไมมาฉลองที่ข้าเล่า
Because you're my little sister.
ก็เจ้าเป็นน้องสาวข้านี่
The Third Young Lady of the Sang family.
คุณหนูสามสกุลซาง
Of course, I have to treat you.
ก็ต้องฉลองกับเจ้าสิ
Let's go.
ไปเถอะ
Young Lady,
คุณหนู
it's no wonder that Young Master
มิน่านายท่านถึงเอาแต่อยากให้
wanted you to study here.
ท่านไปเรียนที่สำนักศึกษา
I can tell that this is a special place
แค่ก้าวเข้ามา
the moment I entered.
ข้าก็รู้สึกว่าต่างกันมากแล้ว
How about it?
เป็นยังไงบ้าง
Do you want to study here too?
เจ้าอยากมาเรียนที่นี่เหมือนกันไหม
Don't tease me, Young Lady.
คุณหนู อย่าล้อข้าเล่นเลย
I am just a servant.
ข้ามีฐานะอะไรกัน
I can understand a storytelling script at best.
อ่านออกก็แค่นิยายเท่านั้น
How could I possibly study here?
จะมาเรียนที่นี่ได้ยังไง
Well, you know more than enough words.
เจ้ายังรู้อักษรไม่มากพอหรือไง
Either way,
กลับกัน
I am confident that there will be
ข้ายิ่งมั่นใจขึ้นทุกทีว่า
more and more female students in the Imperial College in the future,
ศิษย์หญิงในสำนักจะเพิ่มมากขึ้นเรื่อย ๆ
including you.
รวมถึงเจ้าด้วย
Let's go.
ไป
Why isn't
การรับตำแหน่งครั้งนี้
Sang Qi's name on the list?
ทำไมไม่เห็นชื่อซางฉีล่ะ
(Zhuo Wen Yuan, appointed as Vice Minister) His Majesty has already been kind enough
(ศิษย์ที่สอบติด รับราชการ) ฝ่าบาทให้นางเรียนในสำนักศึกษา
to allow her to study here.
ถือว่าไม่เลวแล้ว
His Majesty can't possibly let her become an official.
ยังจะให้นางรับตำแหน่งขุนนางอีกเหรอไง
- That's right. - Indeed.
- นั่นสิ - จริงด้วย
I guess even if women can make it into the list,
ดูท่า ถึงจะสอบติดอันดับ
they'll still have to go home
แต่เป็นสตรียังไงก็ต้องกลับบ้าน
and serve their husbands and take care of their children.
ดูแลสามีและลูกแต่โดยดี
It's more than enough for them to know a few words to manage the household.
รู้จักอักษรบ้าง ทำบัญชีได้ก็พอแล้ว
- Right. - That's right.
- ใช่ - จริงด้วย
I heard
ข้าได้ยินว่า
Deputy Chief went to the Grand Commandant's Residence for marriage.
ซือเย่ไปสู่ขอที่จวนไท่เว่ย
And Yan Xiao Lang
เจ้าเหยียนเสี่ยวหลางนั่น
got together with her maid.
จับคู่กับสาวใช้ข้างตัวนาง
I had already expected this a long time ago.
ข้าน่ะ เดาว่าจะเป็นแบบนี้แล้ว
From the start,
ตั้งแต่แรก
the Sang family already had ulterior motives.
สกุลซางก็มีเป้าหมายอื่นอยู่แล้ว
You're right.
พูดถูก
They come from different classes and backgrounds.
ฐานะไม่เท่าเทียม
She doesn't deserve him.
ไม่คู่ควร
So that's what happened.
ที่แท้ก็แบบนี้เอง
Lian Pian, let's go.
เหลียนเพียน พวกเราไป
Qi, you're here.
อาฉี เจ้ามากันหมดแล้ว
Everyone is already here.
ทุกคนก็มากันแล้ว
I wasn't able to make it to the list.
ศิษย์ไร้ผลงาน
I'm ashamed of facing you, Deputy Chief.
ไม่มีหน้าพบซือเย่
Don't be disappointed.
อย่าเสียใจไปเลย
You've already proven yourself.
เจ้าพิสูจน์ตัวเองแล้ว
You're late.
ทำไมเจ้าเพิ่งมา
What's going on?
เป็นอะไรไป
Why is everybody pulling a long face seeing me here?
พอข้ามาทำไมทุกคนหน้าเศร้าแบบนี้
Everyone got their appointments
พวกท่านอาศัยความสามารถ
with their own merits.
สอบติดรับตำแหน่งขุนนาง
You should all be happy.
ดีใจกันหน่อยสิ
You were on the list as well.
เจ้าก็สอบได้คะแนนดี
But you weren't appointed.
กลับไม่ได้รับตำแหน่ง
But everyone in Bianjing
แต่คะแนนของเจ้า
knows how well you did.
ประชาชนทั่วเปี้ยนจิงต่างรับรู้
This isn't fair.
ไม่ยุติธรรมเลย
That's right.
นั่นสิ
Even those who scored lower marks than you did manage to land positions in the ministry.
พวกที่สอบสู้เจ้าไม่ได้ยังมีตำแหน่งขุนนาง
They should give an explanation for this.
แบบนี้ต้องพูดกันให้รู้เรื่อง
Sang Qi, at least you made it into the list.
ซางฉี อย่างน้อยเจ้าก็มีชื่อติดอันดับ
And what about me?
ข้าน่ะ
I... I have to stay back for another year.
ยังต้องเรียนต่อไปอีกหนึ่งปี
Guo Cheng, didn't you say you wouldn't get drunk off fruit wine?
กั๋วเฉิงจวิน ไหนเจ้าบอกว่าไม่เมาไง
I'm not. I'm not drunk...
ไม่เมา ไม่เมา ไม่เมา
Wine does not make a man drunk, but he is already confused.
สุราไม่เมา แต่คนเมา
We'll leave now.
ไปเถอะ
Excuse us.
ขอทางหน่อย ขอทางหน่อย
Slowly now.
ช้าหน่อย
An entire year...
หนึ่งปีเชียวนะ
That's enough. You guys don't have to comfort me.
เอาล่ะ พวกเจ้าไม่ต้องปลอบข้าแล้ว
I've already decided.
ข้าตัดสินใจแล้ว
I, Sang Qi, won't give up.
ข้าน่ะ ไม่มีวันยอมแพ้แน่
But you're right too.
แต่พวกเจ้าพูดถูก
Since I made the list,
ในเมื่อคะแนนข้าได้ติดประกาศ
I deserve the same opportunities
งั้นก็ข้าสมควรได้โอกาส
as you do. Right?
เช่นเดียวกับพวกเจ้า ถูกไหม
Well, you're a tough one.
เจ้าเข้มแข็งนัก
We've never had a woman as an official in our dynasty.
ราชสำนักนี้ยังไม่เคยมีขุนนางหญิงมาก่อน
I am the first female student of the Imperial College.
ข้าเป็นศิษย์หญิงคนแรกของสำนักศึกษาได้
I, too, can become the first female official in our dynasty.
ข้าก็เป็นขุนนางหญิงคนแรกได้เช่นกัน
That's right, Sang Qi.
ใช่ ซางฉี
I will continue to support you
ข้าจะสนับสนุนเจ้าต่อไป
and help you
และจะช่วยให้เจ้า
get back what you deserve.
ได้รับตำแหน่งที่ควรเป็นของเจ้าด้วย
Qi, we've known each other for many years.
อาฉี พวกเรารู้จักกันมานาน
I'll always support you too.
ข้าเองก็จะสนับสนุนเจ้าเช่นกัน
And I will be joining the Ministry of Personnel soon.
อีกอย่างข้าใกล้จะเข้ากรมขุนนางแล้ว
I will gain more ways and contacts to help you.
จะลองหาวิธีและช่องทางให้
Thank you.
ขอบคุณมาก
Zhuo Wen Yuan.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
As your teacher, I have to advise you.
อาจารย์ขอเตือนเจ้า
You haven't even joined the Ministry of Personnel yet.
ยังไม่ทันเข้ากรมขุนนาง
As a new member joining the court,
ในฐานะขุนนางใหม่เพิ่งเข้างาน
you should learn
เจ้าควรคิดก่อนว่า
how to manage your own duties first.
ควรทำงานของตัวเองให้ดีอย่างไร
The Deputy Chief of the Imperial College is not a position of high status either.
ตำแหน่งซือเย่สำนักศึกษาก็ไม่สูง
Neither do you have much authority.
อำนาจก็ไม่มาก
I will be able
ไม่สู้ข้า
to have more opportunities and a brighter future.
ยังมีโอกาสและอนาคตเสียมากกว่า
It's fine.
ไม่เป็นไร
Zhuo Wen Yuan.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
Thank you for your reminder.
อาจารย์ขอบคุณที่เจ้าตักเตือน
But it's enough for me
แต่เรื่องช่วยซางฉี
to help Sang Qi.
มีข้าก็พอแล้ว
Let's go.
ไปเถอะ
Yan Xiao Lang.
เหยียนเสี่ยวหลาง
Am I drunk?
ข้าเมาแล้วเหรอไง
Ow...
เจ็บ เจ็บ เจ็บ
What my mother said
ที่แม่ข้าพูดวันนั้น
must have made you feel awful.
เจ้าต้องไม่สบายใจแน่
I talked to my mother.
ข้ากลับไปคุยกับท่านแม่แล้ว
Even though she still disapproves...
ถึงนางไม่เห็นด้วยให้ข้าแต่งกับเจ้า
Yan Xiao Lang, maybe we should just give it up.
เหยียนเสี่ยวหลาง เรื่องของเราช่างมันเถอะ
You're still mad after all.
เจ้ายังโกรธอยู่จริงด้วย
I will try my best to get my mother's approval as soon as possible.
ข้าจะรีบปลอบประโลมท่านแม่
Wait for me, all right?
รอข้าได้ไหม
Then what if she won't?
ถ้าเหยียนฮูหยินไม่ยอมใจอ่อน
Would you let go of me first?
เจ้าจะยอมปล่อยมือไหม
I will never.
ให้ตายข้าก็ไม่ยอม
You are the only one for me, Lian Pian.
ชั่วชีวิตนี้ข้าต้องการเหลียนเพียนคนเดียว
Qi, what's on your mind?
อาฉี คิดอะไรอยู่
The appointment?
เรื่องรับตำแหน่งขุนนาง
Or Yan Yan and Lian Pian?
หรือเรื่องเหยียนเหยี่ยนกับเหลียนเพียน
I thought
ข้าหลงคิดว่า
as long as I could get into the Imperial College and study hard,
ถ้าตั้งใจเรียนในสำนักศึกษา
I would be able to change
ก็จะเปลี่ยนความคิดของคนทั่วหล้า
the society's perception of women.
ที่มีต่อสตรีได้
But I tried so hard
เพียงแต่คิดไม่ถึงเลย
and in the end,
พยายามขนาดนี้แล้ว
I was still restrained by societal norms.
สุดท้ายก็ยังถูกคนควบคุม
My name was on the list.
มีชื่อติดอันดับ
But I was not appointed.
แต่กลับไม่ได้รับตำแหน่งขุนนาง
Lian Pian is a wonderful girl.
เหลียนเพียนดีเพียงนั้น
But Madam Yan still said those awful things about her.
ยังถูกเหยียนฮูหยินเอ่ยวาจาบีบคั้น
Qi.
อาฉี
What do you want to do the most
หากเจ้าได้ตำแหน่งขุนนาง
if you receive an appointment?
เจ้าอยากทำอะไรที่สุด
I want to go back to the Imperial College.
ข้าอยากกลับมาสำนักศึกษา
I thought about it a lot.
ข้าคิดมานานแล้ว
From when I entered the Imperial College
ได้พบท่านในสำนักศึกษา
and met you and everyone else
ได้รู้จักทุกคน
until we are going our separate ways now.
มาถึงตอนนี้ต่างก็เข้าทำงาน ในราชสำนักกันหมด
I finally understood
เหมือนข้าจะเข้าใจแล้วจริง ๆ
why my brother wanted me to join the Imperial College
ทำไมท่านพี่ถึงอยากให้ข้ามาเรียนที่นี่
and why he wanted me to strive to get good results.
เป้าหมายที่แท้จริงของการสอบได้
Perhaps he had already expected this.
บางทีเขาอาจเดาผลลัพธ์นี้ได้แต่แรกแล้ว
That's why he wanted me
ดังนั้นเขาจึงหวังว่า
to help the women in this world
ข้าจะเป็นตัวแทนหญิงทั่วหล้า
fight for this opportunity.
ต่อสู้เพื่อให้ได้โอกาสนี้มา
If I can go back to the Imperial College
หากข้ากลับมาสำนักศึกษา
and teach others...
อบรมสั่งสอนศิษย์ต่อไป
No.
ไม่
Even if I could just
รับตำแหน่งเล็ก ๆ
get a minor position in the Imperial College,
ในสำนักศึกษา
that would already have great significance,
นั่นก็มีความหมายอย่างล้ำลึกแล้ว
and I wouldn't disappoint my brother.
ทั้งไม่ผิดต่อความหวังของท่านพี่ด้วย
Qi.
อาฉี
Even if I
ข้าเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
have to risk my position as Deputy Chief,
ต่อให้ต้องแลกด้วยตำแหน่งซือเย่
I will get you the title and accreditation you deserve.
ก็จะช่วยให้เจ้าได้รับตำแหน่งขุนนาง
I said I wanted to become your colleague.
ข้าบอกว่าจะเป็นสหายร่วมงานกับท่านแล้ว
You're usually a stickler for the rules.
ท่านออกจะเข้มงวด
Why aren't you saying anything about it?
ทำไมไม่ขัดข้าสักคำสองคำล่ะ
If you can stay in the Imperial College,
ถ้าเจ้าอยู่ในสำนักศึกษาต่อได้
you will already be the greatest role model
นั่นก็เป็นตัวอย่างที่ดีที่สุด
for women to study.
ของสตรีเข้าเรียนที่สำนักศึกษาแล้ว
That is much more significant than me lecturing students every day.
ยังมีพลังมากกว่าข้าเที่ยว โพนทะนาไปทั่วตั้งเยอะ
Let's go.
ไปเถอะ
(Grand Commandant's Residence)
(จวนไท่เว่ย)
I'll go inside now.
ข้าเข้าไปก่อนล่ะ
Rest early.
กลับไปพักผ่อนเถอะ
Go on.
ไปเร็วเข้า
(Grand Commandant's Residence) Bai Shi.
ป๋ายสือ
I'm going to make a trip to the palace tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้ข้าจะเข้าวังสักเที่ยว
Aren't you going to ask for her hand in marriage?
ไม่ไปสู่ขอแล้วหรือ
I have to ask His Majesty
ต้องไปทวงความยุติธรรม
to give Sang Qi her due appointment first.
เรื่องตำแหน่งของซางฉีกับฝ่าบาทก่อน
If I ask her father for her hand now,
หากสู่ขอก่อน
everyone will know
ทุกคนก็จะรู้ว่า
that she is my wife-to-be.
ซางฉีเป็นคู่หมั้นข้า
Rumors will spread.
ตอนนั้นคนคงลือต่าง ๆ นานา
They'll say that Sang Qi was only able to stay in the Imperial College
หาว่าซางฉีใช้เส้นสาย
because of me.
ถึงอยู่ในสำนักศึกษาต่อได้
I can't let her go through that.
ไม่อาจทำให้นางถูกกดดันได้
You're indeed thoughtful, Young Master.
คุณชายรอบคอบนัก
Yan Yun Zhi.
เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
Yes, Your Majesty.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
You didn't come here
วันนี้เจ้าตั้งใจเข้าวังมา
to show me what a wooden dummy
คงไม่ใช่จะแสดงให้ข้าเห็นว่า
is like, right?
คนใบ้เป็นยังไงหรอกน่ะ
I was thinking of a matter.
กระหม่อมกำลังใคร่ครวญเรื่องหนึ่ง
It concerns Your Majesty's reputation among the people.
เรื่องนี้เกี่ยวพันกับ ชื่อเสียงของฝ่าบาทในหมู่ประชา
I wish to ease Your Majesty's burden.
กระหม่อมช่วยฝ่าบาทแบกรับความกดดัน
So I hope that Your Majesty will allow me
ทั้งหวังว่าฝ่าบาทจะทรงมอบหมายเรื่องนี้
to do so.
ให้กระหม่อมทำให้สำเร็จ
Well, given your hesitance,
ดูท่าทางกระวนกระวายของเจ้าแล้ว
you don't appear convincing.
ข้ารู้สึกไม่อยากเชื่อเท่าไร
What is the matter? Tell me.
มีเรื่องอันใดก็ว่ามาเถิด
I would like to ask Your Majesty
กระหม่อมมาทูลขอฝ่าบาท
to give Sang Qi an official position.
แต่งตั้งตำแหน่งขุนนางให้ซางฉี
That's it?
แค่เรื่องนี้
Would that affect my reputation?
กระทบกับภาพลักษณ์ข้าได้เชียวหรือ
Firstly,
ข้อแรก
Sang Qi did make it into the list.
ซางฉีสอบติดอันดับจริง ๆ
It is within all reason for her to be awarded an official position
ตามหลักแล้วควรได้รับตำแหน่งขุนนาง
and for her to serve the imperial court.
รับใช้ราชสำนัก
Secondly,
ข้อสอง
Sang Qi
ซางฉีเป็นสตรีคนแรกที่
is the first example of a woman studying in the Imperial College.
เข้าเรียนในสำนักศึกษา
Everyone in the nation knows of this.
คนทั่วแคว้นต่างรับรู้
If she can become a female official,
ถ้ายอมมอบตำแหน่งขุนนางหญิงสักคน
then Your Majesty's benevolence and efforts to push for education for all
เช่นนั้นฝ่าบาททรงสนับสนุนการศึกษา
would certainly be a great deed recorded in history.
จะไม่เป็นเรื่องดีน่ายกย่องหรือพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
You make it sound so reasonable.
เจ้าพูดได้น่าฟังนะ
But do you know
แต่เจ้ารู้ไหม
how controversial it is for a woman to become an official?
สตรีเป็นขุนนางจะทำให้ เกิดข้อพิพาทมากนัก
Now, what's this other thing
ไหนเจ้าลองว่ามา
about easing my burden?
จะช่วยข้าแบ่งเบาแรงกดดันอย่างไร
The Imperial College is short of a Manager of the Archive.
สำนักศึกษายังขาดตำแหน่งผู้ดูแลตำรา
It is a position neither too high nor too low.
ตำแหน่งไม่ใหญ่ไม่เล็ก
Sang Qi is the perfect candidate.
เหมาะกับซางฉีพอดี
If someone opposes it,
หากมีคนคัดค้าน
then I, as her teacher
กระหม่อมเป็นทั้งอาจารย์
and her superior,
และหัวหน้านาง
will be the one to face the criticisms.
ความผิดทั้งหมดจะอยู่ที่ตัวกระหม่อม
Your Majesty will not have to worry about that.
ไม่เกี่ยวข้องกับฝ่าบาทเลยสักน้อย
In doing so,
เช่นนี้
Your Majesty will have upheld the fairness of the imperial examination
ฝ่าบาทก็จะรักษากฎการสอบไว้ได้
and quell the disputes among the people.
ซ้ำยังสยบคำวิจารณ์ของชาวบ้าน
Wouldn't that be a win-win?
มิใช่เรื่องดีหรือพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
The Manager of the Archive of the Imperial College.
ผู้ดูแลตำราสำนักศึกษา
Very well.
ดีมาก
(To serve the people. Appoint her as the Manager of the Archive.)
(หนังสือรับตำแหน่งซางฉี ตำแหน่งผู้ดูแลตำราสำนักศึกษา)
Yan Yun Zhi.
เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
What if I was the one
หากข้าเป็นคน
who opposed the decision?
อยู่ฝั่งไม่เห็นด้วยเล่า
Your Majesty has already written the decree of the appointment,
เมื่อครู่ฝ่าบาททรงเขียนหนังสือรับตำแหน่ง
haven't you?
ของซางฉีแล้วมิใช่หรือ
You must have bewitched me with your honeyed words, haven't you?
เจ้ากำลังหลอกล่อช้า ใช่หรือไม่
I wouldn't dare.
กระหม่อมมิกล้า
You wouldn't?
ยังบอกว่ามิกล้าอีก
I think you most certainly would.
เจ้ามันใจกล้านัก
I wouldn't dare.
กระหม่อมมิกล้า
Young Master.
คุณชาย
Bai Shi. Help me change my clothes.
ป๋ายสือ ช่วยข้าเปลี่ยนชุด
We'll make a trip to the Sang Residence.
ไปจวนสกุลซางกัน
I see you have
ดูท่าคุณชาย
good news to tell Miss Sang.
คงมีข่าวดีไปบอกคุณหนูซางแล้ว
Mind your steps.
ระวัง
When did Lan get here?
หลานจีมาตั้งแต่เมื่อไร
Young Master, I asked the servants about it.
คุณชาย ข้าถามแล้ว
Miss Su often comes to visit Madam
ตอนท่านอยู่ข้างนอก แม่นางซู
when you're not around.
มักมาเยี่ยมฮูหยิน
And she usually stays for quite a while
มาทีไรก็อยู่นาน
and gets along very well with Madam.
ซ้ำยังพูดคุยสนุกสนาน
Would you like to greet her?
ท่านว่า จะไปทักดีหรือไม่
Qi Lang!
ชีหลาง
why didn't you tell the family
ข้าขอถามเจ้า เรื่องสำคัญอย่างสู่ขอ
that you went to ask for her hand in marriage?
ทำไมไม่บอกคนที่บ้าน
You're unruly indeed.
ทำผิดลำดับขั้นตอนไปหมด
I've already made it clear
ข้าจะจัดการเรื่องงานแต่งอย่างไร
about who I want to marry.
ก่อนหน้านี้พูดกับพวกท่านชัดเจนแล้ว
But it was against your wishes.
ก็แค่ไม่เป็นไปตามความตั้งใจของท่าน
So both of you pretended you didn't hear.
พวกท่านไม่ฟังก็เท่านั้นเอง
I won't allow you to refute me.
ห้ามเหลวไหล
I'm telling you,
ข้าจะบอกให้
we will never allow you to marry that Sang Qi.
พวกเราไม่ยอมให้เจ้า แต่งกับแม่ซางฉีนั่นแน่
That's fine.
ไม่เห็นด้วย
Then, I'll just leave the family and start a new one on my own.
ข้าก็จะแยกไปตั้งครอบครัวเอง
You...
เจ้า
Young Master.
คุณชาย
Wouldn't this be too direct?
ท่านจะเถรตรงเกินไปหน่อยไหม
Your expression is full of happiness.
ข่าวดีแสดงออกอยู่บนใบหน้า
Miss Sang will be able to know it right away.
คุณหนูซางมองทีเดียวก็รู้แล้ว
Right.
จริงด้วย
You're right.
เจ้าพูดถูก
I should pretend that things didn't go well.
งั้นข้าแสร้งเป็นทำไม่สำเร็จ
And give her a surprise later.
ค่อยบอกความจริงทีหลัง ให้นางตื่นเต้น
That's a good idea.
ความคิดดี
Young Lady, try the snacks I made.
คุณหนูลองชิมขนมที่ข้าเพิ่งทำดูสิเจ้าคะ
All right.
ได้
(Muyan Pavilion)
(ศาลามู่เหยียน)
Qi.
อาฉี
What's going on, Deputy Chief?
ซือเย่เป็นอะไรไป
You don't seem to be in a good mood.
เหมือนอารมณ์ไม่ค่อยดีนัก
I'm sorry.
ขอโทษด้วย
I wasn't able to get His Majesty to let you
เรื่องตำแหน่งผู้ดูแลตำรา
work as the Manager of the Archive.
ข้าช่วยเจ้าไม่ได้
Oh, you had me worried there!
ทำข้าตกใจหมด
I wondered what the matter was.
นึกว่าเรื่องอะไรกัน
Well, this matter is resolved.
เรื่องนี้คลี่คลายแล้ว
So you already know.
ที่แท้เจ้ารู้แล้วนี่เอง
That's right.
ใช่สิ
Thanks to Zhuo Wen Yuan.
ดีที่จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
He had someone from the Ministry of Personnel put a word in.
ให้คนในกรมขุนนางทำเรื่องไป
I'm the Imperial College's Manager of the Archive now.
ตอนนี้ข้าเป็นผู้ดูแลตำราสำนักศึกษา
I'm your colleague now.
เป็นสหายร่วมงานกับท่านแล้ว
Zhuo Wen Yuan?
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
That's right.
- ใช่แล้ว - แต่
He and you...
เขากับเจ้า
Deputy Chief.
ซือเย่
Let's not argue over who gets the credit over this matter.
เรื่องนี้เราไม่ทวงผลงานกันแล้ว
Sang Qi's happiness is the most important thing.
ขอแค่ซางฉีดีใจนั่นสำคัญที่สุด
Deputy Chief was worried
วันนั้นข้าได้ยินซือเย่บอกว่า
that it might be inappropriate
เจ้าเพิ่งเข้ากรมขุนนาง
for you to do such a thing as you just joined the Ministry of Personnel.
เข้าปุ๊บก็ทำเรื่องแบบนี้ เหมือนจะไม่เหมาะเท่าไร
But you already settled it today.
ว่าแต่ทำไมถึงทำได้ไวนักล่ะ
I never try to gain anything from you, Sang Qi.
ข้าไม่ได้ต้องการเอาใจอาฉี
I've always been sincere.
ทั้งไม่มีเป้าหมายอะไร
A thousand gold is worth nothing before your smile.
พันตำลึงยังยากแลกหนึ่งรอยยิ้มของอาฉี
We've been friends for so many years.
พวกเราเป็นพี่น้องกันมานาน
Don't say things like that.
เจ้าอย่าพูดแบบนี้
It grosses me out.
ข้าฟังแล้วขนลุกนัก
Have a seat, Deputy Chief.
ซือเย่นั่งเถอะ
It's fine. There's no need.
ไม่เป็นไร ไม่นั่งแล้ว
I only came to tell you this.
ข้าจะมาบอกเรื่องนี้กับเข้า
Since this matter is already settled,
ในเมื่อเรื่องนี้เรียบร้อยแล้ว
I'll take my leave now.
ข้าขอตัวก่อน
(Muyan Pavilion) You just came, and you're already leaving?
ท่าน ท่านเพิ่งมาก็จะไปแล้วหรือ
I have some matters to attend to.
ข้ายังมีธุระอีก
What a surprise indeed.
ช่างน่าตื่นเต้นนัก
(Secretariat Chancellery)
(จวนจงซู)
Lan.
หลานจี
I heard you've been visiting my mother recently.
ได้ยินว่าระยะนี้เจ้ามาเยี่ยมแม่ข้าบ่อย ๆ
But you didn't tell me about it.
หนำซ้ำไม่บอกข้าสักคำ
You've been very considerate.
ลำบากเจ้าแล้ว
I was only visiting her because I had time on my hands.
ข้าก็ว่างไม่รู้จะไปไหนดี
That's perfect, then.
งั้นก็ดี
There are some things I would like to talk to you about as well.
มีบางอย่างที่ข้าอยากพูดกับเจ้า
It has been a while since we had a chat too.
ข้าเองก็มิได้คุยเล่นกับอวิ๋นจือมานานแล้ว
Let's find a place to talk.
งั้นพวกเราไปหาที่คุยกันเถอะ
Young Master. Miss.
คุณชาย คุณหนู
Lan.
หลานจี
You've visited my mother many times.
เจ้ามาเยี่ยมท่านแม่หลายครั้ง
Are idle talk all that you've done with her?
มาเพื่อคุยเล่นกันนาง อย่างบริสุทธิ์ใจจริงหรือ
You must be bothered
อวิ๋นจือข้องใจ
because I told her
เรื่องที่ข้าบอกท่านป้าว่า
that you asked for Sang Qi's hand in marriage.
ท่านไปสู่ขอซางฉี
She must have tried to stop you, didn't she?
แล้วนางขัดขวางท่านแล้วสินะ
I am serious about that.
สำหรับเรื่องที่ข้าตัดสินใจไปแล้ว
No one and nothing
ไม่ว่าใครเข้ามายุ่ง ใครขัดขวาง
will stop me.
ล้วนไร้ประโยชน์
You think too much.
ท่านคิดมากไปแล้ว
To be very honest with you,
ข้าลองถามใจตัวเอง
my feelings for you ceased
ตอนรู้ข่าวเรื่องท่านไปสู่ขอ
the moment I heard you asked for her hand in marriage.
ใจข้าก็เลิกคิดแล้ว
But as a friend,
เพียงแต่ในฐานะสหาย
I'm worried
วิธีของท่าน
about your actions.
ข้ากังวลอยู่บ้าง
You abruptly went to ask for marrying her at her residence.
ท่านเสี่ยงไปสู่ขอเอง
You must not have made proper preparations.
ไม่ใส่ใจพิธีการใด ๆ
Her family
บ้านนาง
isn't as familiar with you as my family is.
ไม่คุ้นเคยกับท่านเหมือนบ้านข้า
Grand Commandant Sang will definitely not accept it.
ซางไท่เว่ยไม่มีทางรับได้
The Three Letters and Six Rites are essential when it comes to marriages.
แต่งงานต้องมีสามหนังสือหกพิธี
Not only do you need to send your letter of Eight Characters,
ท่านต้องมีใบเกิด
but you will need to write a letter of proposal as well.
ซ้ำยังต้องเขียนหนังสือขอแต่งงาน
Missing any of those will make you appear rash and inappropriate.
มิเช่นนั้นออกจะหุนหันพลันแล่นเกินไป
Thank you for reminding me.
ขอบคุณที่เจ้าเตือนข้า
Oh, right.
จริงสิ
I prepared some snacks for Madam Yan as well.
ข้ายังตั้งใจเตรียมขนมมาให้ท่านป้า
I left them on the horse carriage.
ลืมเอาไว้บนรถม้า
Bai Shi, help Wen Yuan
ป๋ายสือ เจ้าช่วยเหวินยวน
to get those things.
ไปเอาของมาเถอะ
Bai Shi?
ป๋ายสือ
Miss.
คุณหนู
Young Master, should I go?
งั้นคุณชาย ข้าควรไปเอาของ
Or should I...
หรือว่า...
Go on. Come back quickly.
ไปเถอะ รีบไปรีบกลับ
Yes, Young Master.
ขอรับ
Yun Zhi, you mustn't be hasty.
อวิ๋นจือ ท่านอย่ารีบร้อนจนเกินไป
This is an important matter in your life, after all.
นี่เป็นเรื่องใหญ่ในชีวิต
We have been friends for many years.
พวกเราเป็นสหายมานานหลายปี
If there's anything I can help with,
หากมีที่ใดที่ข้าช่วยได้
I hope you won't mind
หวังว่าเจ้าจะวางใจ
and let me know.
บอกกับข้ามาก็พอ
All right. I will.
ได้ แน่นอน
But I heard
แต่ได้ยินว่า
Grand Commandant Sang has already rejected you once.
ซางไท่เว่ยปฏิเสธท่านครั้งหนึ่งแล้ว
Are you sure that you will be successful next time?
ครั้งหน้า ท่านมั่นใจหรือเปล่า
If I fail, I'll just try again.
ครั้งเดียวไม่สำเร็จ เช่นนั้นก็ทำไปเรื่อย ๆ
Until he agrees.
จนกระทั่งเขารับปาก
(Secretariat Chancellery) Bai Shi!
ป๋ายสือ
Is Deputy Chief home?
ซือเย่อยู่จวนไหม
Deputy Chief is home...
ซือเย่อยู่
Wen Yuan.
เหวินยวน
But...
แต่ว่า
Lan is here as well?
หลานจีอยู่ในจวนหรือ
She is here?
นางมาแล้วหรือ
Qi?
อาฉี
(Secretariat Chancellery) Why are you here, Lan?
หลานจีมาได้อย่างไรกัน
I came to keep Madam Yan company.
ข้าว่างไม่มีอะไรจึงมาคุยกับท่านป้า
Well, then, next time,
งั้นอีกหน่อยเวลามาคุยกับท่านป้า
you can bring me along with you.
หลานจีพาข้ามาด้วยได้หรือไม่
Qi, have you been here for long?
อาฉี เจ้ามานานแล้วหรือยัง
No.
ยัง
I was just about to go back.
กำลังจะกลับ
Then, I'll send you back...
งั้นข้าพาเจ้ากลับไป
No need.
ไม่ต้องหรอก
Lan.
หลานจี
You're about to go back, aren't you?
เจ้าจะกลับแล้วเหมือนกันใช่ไหม
Will you give me a ride back?
งั้นช่วยรับข้ากลับไปด้วยได้หรือเปล่า
I can have a chat with you on the carriage as well.
ข้าจะได้พูดคุยกับเจ้าบนรถ
I don't mind. Let's get on the carriage.
ไม่เป็นไร ขึ้นรถม้าเถอะ
Thank you.
ขอบคุณ
What did you tell her just now?
เมื่อครู่เจ้าว่าอะไรนะ
Come to think of it,
จะว่าไป
I should apologize to you, Lan.
ข้าควรขอโทษหลานจี
I understand your feelings for Deputy Chief.
ข้าเข้าใจความรู้สึกของหลานจี ที่มีให้ซือเย่
But you should know
แต่หลานจีควรรู้ว่า
that feelings can't be forced.
เรื่องความรักฝืนกันไม่ได้
But...
ทั้ง ๆ ที่
But I met Yun Zhi first.
ข้ารู้จักอวิ๋นจือมาก่อนหรือ
There is no such thing as who came first in love,
ความรักไม่แบ่งก่อนหลัง
isn't there?
ไม่ใช่หรือ
(Grand Commandant's Residence)
(จวนไท่เว่ย)
Qi!
อาฉี
I know
ข้ารู้
you saw Su Jie Yu and me together today.
วันนี้เจ้าเห็นข้าอยู่กับซูเจี๋ยอวี่
But please don't misunderstand.
อย่าเข้าใจผิดเด็ดขาด
She came to see my mother.
นางมาหาท่านแม่ข้า
There is nothing between us!
พวกเราไม่มีอะไรกันเลย
You look exactly
ท่าทางของท่าตอนนี้
like how I was
เหมือนข้าตอนสอบ
when I wrote the right answer during the exams but crossed it off.
ทั้ง ๆ ที่ตอบถูกแล้วยังขีดทิ้งอีก
Yes. Right.
ถูกแล้ว ใช่
I've reflected upon myself.
ข้าทบทวนตัวเองครั้งแล้วครั้งเล่า
I was wrong.
ข้าผิดไปแล้ว
That has to be the correct answer, right?
นี่คือคำตอบที่ถูกต้องแล้วใช่ไหม
Yan Yun Zhi.
เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
Yes.
อยู่
You are not allowed to be alone with any other woman again.
ต่อไปท่านห้ามอยู่ตามลำพัง กับหญิงใดทั้งนั้น
Of course. I promise.
แน่นอน ข้ารับรองได้
Qi.
อาฉี
I hope
(จวนไท่เว่ย) วันนี้น่ะ
(Grand Commandant's Residence) you will rest early today.
หวังว่าเจ้าจะรีบพักผ่อน
Because I need you to wake up early tomorrow.
เพราะพรุ่งนี้ต้องรบกวนเจ้าตื่นแต่เช้า
Wake up early?
ตื่นเช้า
Grand Commandant Sang.
ซางไท่เว่ย
I came in haste last time.
ครั้งก่อนข้าหุนหันเกินไป
I did not consider all the proper etiquette.
ไม่ทันคิดถึงเรื่องพิธีการไปบ้าง
Today, I have written a letter of proposal,
ครั้งนี้ ข้าเขียนหนังสือขอแต่งงาน
and I have prepared all the bridewealth as well.
ซ้ำของขวัญยังครบถ้วนกว่าครั้งก่อน
Please reconsider, Grand Commandant Sang.
ขอให้ซางไท่เว่ยโปรดพิจารณา
Please allow me to take care of Sang Qi
มอบความสุขชั่วชีวิตของซางฉี
for the rest of her life.
ให้ข้าดูแลด้วย
Father, this will do, right?
ท่านพ่อ ครั้งนี้ใช้ได้หรือยัง
I'm thinking
ข้ากำลังคิดว่า
that such an important matter
เรื่องสำคัญเช่นนี้
cannot be decided so easily.
จะตัดสินใจง่าย ๆ ได้อย่างไร
If you think that there is something lacking,
ถ้าซางไท่เว่ยคิดว่ายังขาดอะไรไป
please let me know immediately.
สั่งการมาได้เลย
I'll make the arrangements right away.
ข้าจะไปทำเดี๋ยวนี้
Father, if you don't accept it,
ท่านพ่อ ถ้าท่านไม่รับ
I will.
ข้ารับแล้วนะ
Hold on.
ช้าก่อน
I'm not late, am I?
ข้าคงไม่ได้มาสายเกินไปหรอกนะ
It looks like you chose to come today as well, Deputy Chief.
ดูท่าซือเย่ก็เลือกวันดีเช่นเดียวกัน
Grand Commandant Sang,
(ใบวันเกิด) ท่านลุง วันนี้ข้ามาสู่ขออย่างเป็นทางการ
Please consider allowing me to marry her.
หวังว่าท่านจะใคร่ครวญ เรื่องงานแต่งของข้ากับซางฉี
Have you gone mad, Zhuo Wen Yuan?
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน เจ้าบ้าไปแล้วเหรอ
This is the most serious decision I have ever made.
นี่คือการตัดสินใจที่จริงจังที่สุด ในชีวิตข้า
You...
เจ้า
It seems
ดูท่า
my Qi is well-liked.
อาฉีบ้านข้าจะมีเสน่ห์ไม่น้อย
I wondered
ข้าล่ะแปลกใจนัก
why you weren't the first to be here
เรื่องสำคัญแบบนี้
for such an important occasion.
ทำไมเจ้าไม่มาเป็นคนแรก
Good.
มาก็ดี
I think you stand a good chance.
ข้าสนับสนุนเจ้า
- Father! - Wait!
- ท่านพ่อ - ช้าก่อน
Grand Commandant Sang,
ท่านลุง
you should know
ท่านน่าจะรู้ว่า
that Sang Qi and I have long been in love, don't you?
ข้ากับอาฉีมีใจตรงกัน
You won't try to separate a pair of lovers, would you?
ท่านจะจับคู่ผิดฝาผิดตัวอย่างนั้นหรือ
(Letter of Eight Characters) Grand Commandant Sang is just observant.
ท่านลุงมีความคิดละเอียดถี่ถ้วน
He knew that Sang Qi and I grew up together.
ดูออกว่าข้ากับอาฉี โตด้วยกันมาแต่เด็ก
I understand and care for Sang Qi
ข้าเข้าใจและห่วงใยอาฉี
more than you do.
เทียบกันแล้วไม่ด้อยว่าท่านเลย
Then have you asked Sang Qi's opinion in this matter?
เจ้าเคยถามความเห็นนางไหม
Zhuo Wen Yuan.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน
I have always thought of you as my closest friend.
ข้าเห็นเจ้าเป็นสหายสนิทที่สุดมาตลอด
We have always been
ระหว่างพวกเรา
just that as well.
ขีดเส้นแบ่งความสัมพันธ์ไว้ชัดเจน
You've seen how Deputy Chief
เรื่องที่ผ่านมาของข้ากับซือเย่
and I got together.
เจ้าก็เห็นมาโดยตลอด
Why are you doing this today?
ทำไมวันนี้ยังทำเช่นนี้ด้วย
Hurry up and go back.
รีบกลับไปเถอะ
Leave!
ไปสิ
Qi.
อาฉี
I know you and Deputy Chief are in love.
ข้ารู้ว่าเจ้ากับซือเย่รักชอบพอกัน
But I have a chance to fight
แต่ข้าก็ทำเพื่อความสุขของตัวเอง
for my love as well, don't I?
ต่อสู้เพื่อโอกาสไม่ใช่หรือไง
Besides,
อีกอย่าง
I think Grand Commandant Sang favors me more.
ข้าคิดว่าท่านลุงเข้าข้างข้ามากกว่า
One's parents should have the final say when it comes to the matter of marriage.
งานแต่งงานต้องเชื่อฟังพ่อแม่
My marriage
งานแต่งของข้า
will be decided by myself.
ข้าตัดสินใจเอง
Qi.
อาฉี
In that case,
ในเมื่อเป็นเช่นนี้
we'll settle this the Sang way.
งั้นก็ตัดสินด้วยกฎสกุลซาง
Fine.
ได้
Marriage is not a game.
เรื่องแต่งงานมิใช่เรื่องเด็กเล่น
Don't blame your daughter
ท่านอย่าโทษที่ลูก
for bullying an old man like you.
รังแกคนแก่ก็แล้วกัน
Qi!
อาฉี
Your father is
พ่อเจ้าน่ะ
as skilled as ever.
คือกระบี่ล้ำค่าไม่ขึ้นสนิม
Qi!
อาฉี
Qi, please stop messing around.
อาฉีอย่าเหลวไหลเลย
Grand Commandant Sang!
ซางไท่เว่ย
Qi!
อาฉี
What are you guys doing?
พวกท่านทำแบบนี้ทำไม
It is pointless for Qi and I
เราสองพ่อลูกหมุนไปหมุนมาอยู่ที่นี่
to fight here.
จะมีความหมายอะไรกัน
You guys should be the ones doing this.
เรื่องนี้ต้องยกให้พวกเจ้าสองคน
A duel to decide the marriage.
งั้นพวกเจ้าก็ประลองกันเลือกคู่
Whoever wins will get to marry Qi.
ใครชนะก็แต่งกับอาฉี
Father.
ท่านพ่อ
I told you. I'll decide my own marriage.
ข้าบอกแล้วว่าเรื่องแต่งงานข้าตัดสินใจเอง
What are you trying to do?
ท่านมาไม้ไหนเนี่ย
I get the final say in the Sang family.
เรื่องสกุลซางต้องฟังข้าเท่านั้น
I'll decide the rules.
กฎข้ากำหนดเอง
You...
ท่าน
I have the say.
เรื่องนี้ต้องฟังข้า
How about it?
สองท่านว่าอย่างไร
Do you dare to duel?
พวกเจ้ากล้าขึ้นประลองไหม
- Why wouldn't I?
ทำไมจะไม่กล้า
Welcome everyone
ขอต้อนรับทุกท่าน
to the Sang Residence's duel for Young Lady Sang's marriage.
ร่วมงานประลองเลือกคู่สกุลซาง
We hope that all young and capable gentlemen will participate.
หวังว่าคุณชายทั้งหลายจะเข้าร่วมประลอง
Welcome everyone
ขอต้อนรับทุกท่าน
to the Sang Residence's duel for Young Lady Sang's marriage.
ร่วมงานประลองเลือกคู่สกุลซาง
We hope that all young and capable gentlemen will participate.
หวังว่าคุณชายทั้งหลายจะเข้าร่วมประลอง
Don't worry.
วางใจเถอะ
(Haoran Hall) Today, the Sang family
วันนี้ตระกูลซาง
has set up a stage here.
ตั้งเวทีประลองนี้ขึ้นมา
There are two things
มีเรื่องสำคัญสองเรื่อง
we would like to announce to the people of Bianjing.
จะประกาศให้ชาวเมืองเปี้ยนจิงได้ทราบ
First of all, the Sang family
เรื่องแรก สกุลซางเรา
has a new young lady.
มีคุณหนูเพิ่มขึ้นมาอีกคน
My newly adopted daughter,
ก็คือลูกสาวบุญธรรมข้า
Lian Pian.
เหลียนเพียน
Great!
- ดี ดี - ดี
Secondly,
เรื่องที่สอง
we will be hosting a duel for my daughter, Sang Qi's marriage
สกุลซางจัดงานประลองเลือกคู่
right here.
ในที่นี้
Everyone here can be a participant
ทุกท่านสามารถร่วมประลองได้
as well as a witness.
ทั้งยังเป็นพยานได้
The Sang family is not concerned
สกุลซางไม่สนใจสถานะ
about statuses and backgrounds.
ไม่สนใจชาติกำเนิด
As long as you are a young, unmarried man
ขอแค่อายุเหมาะสม
of a suitable age, good character,
เป็นหนุ่มโสดนิสัยดี
and are able to stand your ground
ขอเพียง
on this stage,
เอาชนะบนลานประลองแห่งนี้
you may ask for Second Young Lady Sang Qi's hand in marriage.
ก็สามารถสู่ขอคุณหนูรองซางฉีได้
This is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity.
อย่าพลาดโอกาสเชียว
Great!
- ดี ดี - ดี
Young Master.
คุณชาย
Didn't Grand Commandant Sang say
ซางไท่เว่ยบอกว่า
it was just a duel between you and Wen Zhuo Yuan?
จะให้ท่านประลองกับ จั๋วเหวินหย่วนสองคนมิใช่หรือ
Why has it turned into a battle
ทำไมกลายเป็นว่า
where every capable young man is allowed to join?
ชายหนุ่มทุกคนในเมืองเข้าร่วม
Grand Commandant Sang is most right to say that.
ซางไท่เว่ยเอ่ยเช่นนี้ถึงจะรอบคอบ
If it was just a duel between
หากให้ข้ากับจั๋วเหวินหย่วนสองคน
Zhuo Wen Yuan and me,
ขึ้นเวทีประลองเท่านั้น
it may be a fair fight,
ถึงจะเป็นการแข่งอย่างยุติธรรม
but there are so many pairs of eyes here.
แต่ในสายตาของคนหมู่มาก
People may suspect and say things about the Sang family,
ยากนักจะไม่ให้วิจารณ์สกุลซาง
and cause disputes between our families.
ทำให้เราสองสกุลกลายเป็นอริกัน
It risks causing tensions.
ถูกครหาได้
It makes sense when you put it that way.
ว่าไปก็ถูก
Besides, I know
อีกอย่างข้ารู้ว่า
that the Sang family has been practicing martial arts for generations.
สกุลซางเป็นนักบู๊
They've been staying at the frontier for many years. They favor the strong.
กรำศึกชายแดนหลายปี ชื่นชมผู้แข็งแกร่ง
If I can't even handle the others,
หากข้าจัดการกระทั่งคนอื่นไม่ได้
how would I earn Grand Commandant Sang's approval?
แล้วจะเข้าตาซางไท่เว่ยได้อย่างไร
Aren't you going to warm up?
ท่านไม่ยืดเส้นสักหน่อยหรือ
No need.
ไม่จำเป็น
Then, remember this.
งั้นท่านก็จำไว้
Take care of yourself out there.
หลังจากขึ้นเวทีแล้วต้องรักษาตัว
Don't get hurt.
อย่าบาดเจ็บเด็ดขาด
I don't want to see bruises on your face.
ข้าไม่อยากเห็นหน้าท่านมีรอยแผล
Don't worry.
วางใจเถอะ
I am your senior.
เจ้าเรียกข้าเป็นศิษย์พี่แล้ว
Zhuo Wen Yuan's skills are inferior to mine.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วนย่อมไม่เหนือกว่าข้าแน่
Just get ready to become my wife.
เจ้ารอเป็นภรรยาข้าเถอะ
Grand Commandant Sang,
ท่านลุง
I will win for sure.
ข้าจะต้องเอาชนะการประลองนี้ให้ได้
I won't let Yan Yun Zhi
ข้าไม่ยอมให้เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
take Sang Qi away.
แย่งซางฉีไปแน่
I may have organized this duel.
ถึงข้าจัดงานประลองเลือกคู่ขึ้นมา
But my intention
แต่ความตั้งใจของข้า
was not to go against my daughter's will.
ไม่คิดเป็นปรปักษ์กับลูกสาว
I'm giving both you and Yan Yun Zhi a chance
แค่ให้โอกาสเจ้ากับเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือ
to prove your determination to marry her.
แสดงความมุ่งมั่นที่จะแต่งกับอาฉีเท่านั้น
Your fate
ความสุขของพวกเจ้า
lies in your own hands.
ล้วนอยู่ในกำมือตัวเอง
If you can do it, fight.
ถ้าทำได้ ก็จงเอาชีวิตเข้าแลก
If you can't, give up.
ถ้าไม่ไหว ก็ยอมรับชะตาซะ
Yes.
เข้าใจแล้ว
Zhuo Wen Yuan, the battle hasn't begun yet.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน งานประลองยังไม่เริ่ม
It's not too late for you to leave now.
ตอนนี้ถอนตัวยังทัน
Qi, if you're trying to get me to quit,
อาฉี ถ้าคิดจะเกลี้ยกล่อมให้ข้าถอย
you can stop now.
งั้นอย่าพูดเลย
I am not someone who quits
ข้าไม่ใช่พวกยอมแพ้
before even trying.
โดยไม่ทันจะเริ่ม
Qi, you can choose not to choose me.
อาฉี เจ้าไม่เลือกข้าได้
You can choose Yan Yun Zhi.
เจ้าจะเลือกเยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือต่อไปก็ได้
But you can't stop me from pursuing you
แต่เจ้าไม่อยากหยุดยั้งไม่ให้ข้า
and trying to marry you.
สู่ขอเจ้าได้
Zhuo Wen Yuan, you and I have been friends for many years.
จั๋วเหวินหย่วน เจ้าเป็นสหายข้ามาหลายปี
I don't want to see both of you
ข้าไม่อยากเห็น
fight and get into a dispute out there.
พวกเจ้าต้องเป็นอริกันบนเวทีนี้จริง ๆ
I don't want to just speak without actions.
ข้าไม่อยากเอาแต่ใช้ปากพูด
I want to prove my words.
ไม่ลงมือกระทำ
I am going out there for sure.
เวทีนี้ ข้าขึ้นไปแน่
Out of the way.
หลบหน่อย หลบ
What's going on?
ทำอะไรกัน
Back off!
หลบไป
Sang Qi, how could you do this?
อาฉีเจ้าทำเกินไปแล้ว
How could you have Yan Yun Zhi fight with someone over you?
กล้าทำให้เยี่ยนอวิ๋นจือต่อสู้เพื่อเจ้า
I won't forgive you
ถ้าเขาบาดเจ็บ
if he gets hurt!
ข้าไม่ปล่อยเจ้าไปแน่
Miss Song.
คุณหนูซ่ง
You must have gotten all dressed up
วันนี้แต่งตัวเฉิดฉัน
to try and steal the attention today.
คงมาทำตัวเด่นเหนือข้าแล้ว
But...
แต่ว่า
That scent on you
กลิ่นบนตัวเจ้า
is way too strong.
ออกจะแรงไปหน่อย
Did you use all of the perfume and aromatics
นี่เจ้าอาบเครื่องหอม
in a perfume store?
ทั้งร้านเครื่องหอมมาหรือไร
You're just tasteless.
เจ้ามันไม่มีรสนิยม
This is a rare type of aromatic
นี่คือเครื่องหอมหายาก
my father specifically got me.
ที่ท่านพ่อข้าให้คนส่งมา
I'm the only one who has this in all of Bianjing.
ทั่วทั้งเมืองข้ามีเพียงคนเดียว
Perhaps I am too ignorant, after all.
บางทีข้าอาจความรู้น้อยไป
I've never smelled something so pungent.
ถึงไม่เคยได้กลิ่นที่ฉุนเช่นนี้
This is strange.
แปลกจริง
There are so many people here.
วันนี้คนมากันพร้อมหน้า
But why isn't Yan Xiao Lang around?
เหยียนเสี่ยวหลางทำไมไม่มา
Can you stop fanning yourself?
เจ้าเลิกพัดได้ไหม
It seems no one dares to come onto the stage.
เห็นท่าไม่มีใครกล้าขึ้นมา
If there is no one else,
หากไม่มีใครขึ้นมาละก็
we will proceed to the final duel with both of them.
งั้นข้าจะให้พวกเขาประลองแล้ว
Whoever wins
ใครชนะ
will be able to marry my Sang Qi.
จะได้แต่งงานกับซางฉีลูกสาวข้า
Song Luo Tian from the Song family will duel!
ซ่งลั่วเทียนสกุลซ่งเข้าร่วมการแข่ง
♪As our fate intertwined, which life should we pick?♪
♪รอโชคชะตาที่เริ่มครอบงำชีวิต♪
♪I'm willing to this life for a chance to meet you in every life♪
♪ยินยอมแลกทั้งชีวิตให้แก่กันและกัน♪
♪Many woes and sorrows fill my existence♪
♪มีความคิดนับพันติดค้างในใจข้า♪
♪Makes us fall in love with each other♪
♪กลายเป็นความรักลึกซึ้งของกันและกัน♪
♪That's how I come to this life♪
♪ข้าถึงได้มีชั่วชีวิตนี้♪
♪If not letting go of my past♪
♪หากการเริ่มหวนคิดเรื่องเก่า♪
♪Becomes my mistake♪
♪กลายเป็นความผิดพลั้งของข้า♪
♪Then I shall not make that mistake♪
♪ข้าย่อมไม่คิดสิ่งนั้น♪
♪This beautiful story♪
♪หากเรื่องราวที่สมบูรณ์ดั่งสัญญา♪
♪Is like the way I look when I make up my mind♪
♪บังเอิญพบกับตัวข้าที่แน่วแน่♪
♪But my heart changed its mind♪
♪ดวงใจกลับแปรเปลี่ยนจุดเริ่มต้น♪
♪At the dawn♪
♪ในห้วงเวลาที่น้ำค้างหยด♪
♪What an unexpected love♪
♪ไม่รู้ว่าชะตาความรักเป็นอย่างไร♪
♪And so I wrote my words with joy♪
♪ข้าเขียนบทกวีแห่งความสุข♪
♪I have accepted this life I reincarnated in♪
♪ข้าก็จะยอมรับช่วงชีวิตที่หมุนเวียน♪
♪May this budding romance♪
♪นำความรักจากความเฉยชา♪
♪Develop into something unforgettable♪
♪หล่อหลอมจนเป็นลวดลายที่ชัดเจน♪